Guide to the World Federation of Trade Unions Records
World Federation of Trade Unions Records
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
World Federation of Trade Unions Records
1945-1973
5595
World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU)
4 linear ft.
Correspondence, minutes, proceedings.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
This collection consists of records of the World Federation of Trade Union's conferences, including agendas, reports, and speeches. Included is an index.
4 cubic feet
The World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU) was founded at a world labor conference in London, England in 1945. Its stated goal was the development of better understanding and joint programs among the national unions of various countries. The WFTU soon came under the control of affiliated communist unions. Communist domination of the WFTU resulted in the disaffiliation of the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) in 1949. The CIO then joined with other labor organizations opposed to the politics of the WFTU to form the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions.
Records consist primarily of the minutes, proceedings and reports of WFTU officers and governance committees, produced and presented at WFTU conferences held in London (1945, 1949); Paris (1945, 1947, 1949); Moscow (1946, 1970); Trieste (1946); Prague (1947, 1958, 1963, 1967); Geneva (1948); Rome (1948); Peking (1949); Budapest (1950, 1969, 1972); Bucharest (1950, 1971); Berlin (1951, 1958); Vienna (1951-1953); Warsaw (1954, 1959); Sofia (1956, 1966); Nicosia (1966); Khartoum (1970); and Varna (1973). Also include some personal correspondence and WFTU materials collected by Adolf F. Germer (socialist; official and organizer of the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) and various coal and petroleum workers' unions) during his attendance as the CIO delegate to the WFTU conference (Prague, 1946), and his membership on the WFTU Committee on German Affairs (1947).
Governance records (1945-1973) include minutes, resolutions and proceedings of the WFTU Executive Bureau, General Councils, and committees (1945-1973) and of joint meetings of the WFTU and International Trade Secretariats (1948); also financial statements of the WFTU (1945-1949).
Reports and publications (1946-1973) consist mainly of unpublished reports and some pamphlets produced and presented at the annual sessions of the Executive Bureau and General Councils of the WFTU; also reports pertaining to special policies and activities of the WFTU. Materials pertaining to the WFTU's internal organization discuss or document the creation of WFTU international trade departments and negotiations between WFTU and International Trade Secretariats (1947-1948); establishment of WFTU departments on professionals, metal trades workers, miners, textile workers, and agricultural and forestry workers (1946-1964); charter of union rights (1954); and various revisions and amendments to the WFTU constitution (1948-1970). Also include documents regarding relations between the WFTU and the United Nations, International Labour Organization, Congress of Industrial Organizations, American Federation of Labor, and Allied Commission (Berlin); and various conferences, including the Pan Asiatic Trade Union Conference, the Pan Africa Conference, and the World Trade Union Congress (1948-1973).
Also, WFTU policy statements regarding union activity and socioeconomic conditions in Spain, Iran, Egypt, South Africa, Greece, Occupied Germany and various colonial countries (1946); activities in Trieste, Tunisia, Iran, Japan, Austria, the international coal countries, Greece and Portugal (1947-1948); in Burma, Italy, Israel, and Japan (1949-1952); and in the European coal and steel community, Vietnam, colonial and newly independent countries, and Palestine (1953-1965).
Additional reports (some of which were produced by WFTU officers Louis Saillant, Leon Jouhaux, S. Rostovsky, Fernando Santi and R. Vivimari) regard WFTU policy on: professional workers, migrations, postwar reconstruction and grants-in-aid, equal work and equal wages for women workers, and union rights (1946-1948); racial discrimination, currency devaluations, the international labor movement, and the WFTU delegation to Israel (1949-1950); social security, struggles for political and union rights for international workers (1951-1952); atomic war and peace, women workers and young workers (1953-1958); and the European Economic Community and monopolies, protection of victims of anti-union repression, and general WFTU activities (1959-1966); also, international union relations, unions and scientific and technical progress, unity among unions, monetary crises, economic and social demands of workers in capitalist
countries, and union education (1967-1973).
Additional documents collected by Adolf F. Germer (CIO delegate to the WFTU) include various bulletins and press releases of the U.S. military government in Germany; pamphlets and reports pertaining to the trade union movement, social welfare, women workers, and political issues in Czechoslovakia (1945-1947); and press releases and publications of the Freier Deutscher Gewerkschaftsbund.
Also, a file of correspondence between Germer and various WFTU leaders, American union leaders and politicians. Correspondents include Philip Murray (president, CIO); Louis Saillant (general secretary, WFTU); William Green (president, American Federation of Labor); Wayne Morse (U.S. senator) and Leon Blum (prime minister of France). The correspondence generally pertains to WFTU conferences, publications, development of international unionism, and relations between unions and the WFTU (1944-1947).
Blum, Leon, 1872-1950; Germer, Adolph; Green, William, 1872-1952; Jouhaux, Leon, 1879-1954; Morse, Wayne.; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952.; Rostovsky, S.; Saillant, Louis.; Santi, Fernando.; Vivimari, R.; Allied Commission.; American Federation of Labor.; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); International Labour Organization.; Pan Africa Conferences.; Pan Asiatic Trade Union Conference.; United Nations.; World Federation of Trade Unions.; World Trade Union Congress.
Anti-unionism.; Coal mining industry. Europe.; Collective bargaining. Professions.; Labor and laboring classes. Socioeconomic status.; Steel industry. Europe.; Trade-union solidarity.; Trade-unions. Agricultural workers. International cooperation.; Trade-unions. Coal-miners. International cooperation.; Trade-unions. Foresters. International cooperation.; Trade-unions. Metal-workers. International cooperation.; Trade-unions. Miners. International cooperation.; Trade-unions. Textile workers. International cooperation.; Workers' education.
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Collections: 5256: Adolph Germer Papers 5396 mf: World Federation of Trade Unions Reports and Minutes on Microfilm
- 1945-1947 (Box 1)
  - Federation Syndicale Mondial (FSM)., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    "Reunion du Bureau Syndicale", October 6-9, 1945, 30 page mimeographed typescript (mimeographed ts), brittle (bt) "Reunion du Bureau Executif," December 21-22, 1945, 21 page mimeographed typescript, brittle
  - Federation Syndicale Mondiale, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    "Session du Bureau Executif," February 22-25, 1946, 29 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Rapport au Bureau Executif de la FSM sur la representation de la FSM au sien del Organisation des Nations Unies (ONU)" February 22-24, 1946, 15 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Reports on trade departments presented to the Executive Bureau-Paris-1946," 26 page mimeographed typescript, brittle
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    "Session of the Executive Committee," June 22-27, 1946, 106 page mimeographed typescript, brittle
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Session of the Executive Bureau," June 17-20, 1946, 80 page mimeographed typescript, brittle
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Report of the commission of the WFTU to investigate conditions in Germany adopted by the Executive Bureau in Moscow," June 17-20, 1946, 63 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "[Provisional] Report of the commission of the WFTU to investigate conditions in Germany," 1946, 73 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    "Report on the position, the activity and the decisions of the World Trade Union Movement with regard to the struggle against the dictatorship of General Franco in Spain - Presented to the Executive Bureau and the Executive Committee of the WFTU," June 17-20, 1946, 13 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report on the relations between the World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU) and the Inter-Allied Control Council in Berlin - Presented to the Executive Bureau and the Executive Committee of the WFTU," June 1946, 16 page mimeographed typescript (mimeographed ts), brittle (bt). "Report on the internal organization of departments of the WFTU - Presented to the Executive Committee of the WFTU," June 17-20, 1946, 9 page mimeographed typescript, brittle
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    "Report on the creation of the International Trade Departments presented to the executive Bureau and Executive Committee of the WFTU," June 1946, 25 page mimeographed typescripts, brittle. "Report on the imprisonment of Comrade el Hedarrek member of the General Council of the WFTU and on the restrictions imposed on the exercise of trade union rights in Egypt - Presented to the Executive Committee of the WFTU," June 1946, 6 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report on the help of the WFTU to the trade unions in colonial countries or mandated territories - Presented by the General Secretary of the WFTU to the Executive Bureau and Executive Committee," June 1946, 30 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    "Report of the representation of the WFTU within the United Nations Organization - Presented by the General Secretary to the Executive Committee of the WFTU," June 1946, 48 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Memorandum on the creation of the activity and admission to the WFTU of the Greek General Federation of Labor- Presented to the Executive bureau and Executive Committee of the WFTU," June 1946, 11 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    "Session of the Executive Bureau," September 20-24, 1946, 90 page mimeographed typescript, brittle
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    "Report of the General Secretary of the WFTU on his mission of Iran-Presented to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU," September 1946, 18 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report of the Commission of Enquiry on Tunisia - Presented to the Executive Bureau," September 1946, 7 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report from Mr. Verret concerning his delegation at the 5th Session of the UNRA Council in Geneva - Presented to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU," September 1946, 5 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report concerning the representation of the WFTU at the United Nations Food and Agricultural Organisation - Presented to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU," September 1946, 4 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Rapport concernant les refugees at les personnes deplacees presente au Bureau Executif de la FSM," September 1946, 15 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    "Report by Leon Jouhaux, Vice-President of the WFTU on his visit to Greece to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU," September 1946, 19 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report concerning the relations of the WFTU with the Allied Control Council in Berlin since the session of the Executive Committee of June 1946 - Presented to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU," September 1946, 6 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report on the representation of the World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU) within the United Nations Organization (UNO) - Presented by the General Secretary to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU," September 1946, 20 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    "Report on the meeting of the Trade Unions of Trieste," October 18-20, 1946, 32 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Union (WFTU), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    "Session of the Executive Bureau," December 9-16, 1946, 152 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    "Report on the representation of the WFTU within the UNO - Presented by the General Secretary to the Executive Bureau o the WFTU," December 1946, 14 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report on the strike of the South African Miners," December 1946, 13 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    "Provisional report of the 2nd WFTU Enquiry Commission on the Situation in Germany," January-February 1947, 88 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    "Report on migrations," January 9-10, 1947, 51 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    "Report on the fact-finding mission to Africa," February-April 1947, 78 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    "General Secretary's report on the WFTU enquiry in Japan," March-April 1947, 107 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    "Report on visit to Greece," April 26-May 3, 1947, 13 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    "Sessions of the Executive Bureau held in Prague," June 2-5, 7, 15, 1947 90 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    "Session of the Executive Committee," June 6-7, 1947, 48 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Union, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    "Trade Union situation in Iran, report of the delegation of the WFTU to Iran - Presented to the Executive Bureau Executive Committee and General Council," June 2-14, 1947, 33 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Reports on the trade union situation in Tunisia - Report of T. McWhinnie on the first Congress of the UGTT - Report of Mustapha el Kriss on his trade union inquiry - Presented to the Executive Bureau and Committee," June 2-7, 1947, 43 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report on the Trade Union situation in Trieste- Presented to the Executive Bureau, Executive Committee and General Council," June 2-14, 1947, 8 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    "Inquiry, Conference and Resolutions concerning the situation in Austria - Report presented to the Executive Bureau, Executive Committee and General Council," June 2-14, 1947, 57 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Pan-African Trade Union Information Conference: Report and conclusions - Presented to the Executive Bureau, Executive Committee and General Council," June 2-14, 1947, 15 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Draft preliminary report of the delegation to Japan and Korea," 1947, 23 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    "Situation of the coal industry in the world," 1947, 120 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
- 1947-1950 (Box 2)
  - World Federation of Trade Unions., 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    "Minutes of the joint meeting of the delegation of the Executive Bureau of the WFTU with the Advisory Committee of the ITS," August 19, 1947, 32 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    " Session of the Executive Bureau," November 18-24, 1947, 124 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU); Federation Syndicale Mondiale (FSM), 1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    WFTU: "Executive Bureau - Statement on the Trade Union situation in Germany," November 18-24, 1947, 13 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. FSM: "Note-Concernant le probleme des departments professionals - Presente au Bureau Executif," November 18-24, 1947, 7 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. WFTU: "Introductory report on the relation between the WFTU and the I.L.O. - Presented to the Executive Bureau," November 18-24, 1947, mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    "Report on the 5th session of the Economic and Social Council of the U.N.O. - Presented to the Executive Bureau," November 18-24, 1947, 28 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    "Supplement to the report of the Trade Department of the WFTU," 1947, 5 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Conclusions," 1947, 9 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Addition to the conclusions of the report about Germany," 1947, 1 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Note for the information of members of the Executive Bureau," 1947, 7 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    "session of the Executive Bureau," April 30-May 2, 1948, 61 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    "Report on the trade union situation in Germany - Presented to the Executive Bureau and Executive Committee of the WFTU," April 30-May 2, 1948, 13 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report on the activity of the WFTU concerning the principles of equality of wages for equal work between male and female labour. Submitted to the Executive Bureau and Committee of the WFTU," May 2, 1948, 37 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report on the trade union situation in Greece. Submitted to the Executive Bureau and Committee of the WFTU," April 30-May 2, 1948, 22 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report on negotiations between the ILO and the WFTU. Submitted to the Executive Board and Committee of the WFTU," April 30-May 2, 1948, 6 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    "Notice for the members of the Executive Committee, Rome," May 1968, 6 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report on the creation of the Trade Departments. Submitted to the Executive Bureau and Committee of the WFTU," April 30-May 2, 1948, 8 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report on the relations between the WFTU with the Economic Council of UNO. Submitted to the Executive Bureau and Committee of the WFTU," April 30-May 2, 1948, 15 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Report on the activities of the WFTU in connection with the guarantee of exercise and extension of trade union rights. Submitted to the Executive Bureau and Committee of the WFTU," April 30-May 2, 1948, 21 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    "Session of the executive Committee," May 5-10, 1948, 136 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    "Report concerning breaches of trade union right submitted to the United Nations Economic and Social Council by the WFTU," June 1948, 35 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    "Session of the Executive Bureau," September 17-21, 1948, 103 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Joint meeting of the WFTU Executive Bureau and the representatives of the ITS," September 14-16, 1948, 51 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    "For the meeting of the Executive Bureau - Item 9 of the draft agenda - Information concerning the work of the members of the Commission of Enquiry to Japan," September 1948, 5 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "For the meeting of the Executive Bureau - Point 7 of the draft agenda - Report on the trade union situation in Germany," September 1948, 40 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    "For the session of the Executive Bureau - Item 3 of the draft agenda - Note on the decision and correspondence concerning a Pan-Asiatic Trade Union Conference," September 1948, 9 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "For the meeting of the Executive Bureau - Item 4 of the draft agenda - Report on the seventh session of the Economic Aid and Social Council," September 1948, 30 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "For the meeting of the Executive Bureau - Point 5 of the draft agenda - Draft concerning a Trade Union Conference on Hygiene, Security at Work and Health Policy," September 1948, 6 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "For the meeting of the Executive Bureau - Item 12 on the draft agenda - Communication from the General Secretary on the trade union situation in Mexico and Latin America," September 1948, 9 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    "Economic and Social Services. Documentary note on post-war reconstruction and economic aid," 1948, 167 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    "Session of the executive Bureau," January 17-22, 1949, 136 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    "Session of Executive Committee," January 26-February 1, 1949, 188 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    "Letter from the General Secretary to the affiliated national centers re incidents at January 19 session of the Executive Bureau," 1949, 10 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    "Executive Bureau of the WFTU - Item I of the draft agenda - Report of the implementation of the decisions and resolutions of the 2nd World Trade Union Congress," November 11-14, 1949, 35 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Executive Bureau of the WFTU - Item II of the draft agenda - Report on the International Day for Peace on October 2," November 11-14, 1949, 26 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Executive Bureau of the WFTU - Item III of the draft agenda - Report on the Trade Departments," November 11-14, 1949, 12 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. "Executive Bureau of the WFTU - Item IV of the draft agenda - Report on the tasks and activities of the WFTU at UNO and specialized agencies," November 11-14, 1949, 11 page mimeographed typescript, brittle. :Executive Bureau of the WFTU - Item VII of the draft agenda - Report on the devaluation," November 11-14, 1949, 7 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    "Report on social and economic discrimination against workers for reasons of race or color (This report was sent to the UN Secretary General on December 13, 1949, to be inserted on the agenda of the 10th session of the Economic and Social Council)," December 1949, 47 page mimeographed typescript, brittle.
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 20)